Guide to the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project, 2005-2009: SdArch 29
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project
2005-2009
Special Collections, James Madison University
Kerr, Daniel
SdArch 29
.99 cubic feet; 3 boxes; 103 cds
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to the oral histories is governed by agreements with the interviewees. In the event that interviewees did not grant permission for full online access to recordings and documents, transcripts (if available) are open to research in the Special Collections Reading Room. Pseudonyms are used when requested by the interviewees.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated in two installments. The first set of 20 interviews and background materials were donated by Dr. Daniel Kerr, History Professor at James Madison University, in June of 2006. The second set of 79 interviews and background materials were donated on June 1, 2010, by Professor Daniel Kerr.
Separated Materials
Audio cds are housed in media cabinet.
Bio/Historical Note
The Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project was initiated by Professor Daniel Kerr at James Madison University in Fall 2005 as a component of the course, HIST 339: Selected Themes in U.S. History. Students conducted and transcribed the interviews of Shenandoah Valley residents, primarily in Rockingham and Augusta Counties. From 2006-2009, Professor Daniel Kerr had students conduct oral histories in additional courses, namely HIST 339: US Environmental History and HIST 441/641: Oral History and Social Justice.
Scope and Content
The Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project, 2005-2009, is comprised of audio interviews, transcripts, background papers, digital photographs and supplementary digital material related to Shenandoah Valley residents, primarily in Rockingham and Augusta Counties.
Each interview typically consists of an interview guide, an interview journal/log, the transcript of the interview, the recorded interview, and, when present, images and other supplementary material. The interview guide contains questions that the interviewer would have used during the interview. The interview journal offers the interviewer's insights and experiences before, during and after the interview. The transcripts for each interview provide biographical details of the interviewee, as well as the transcription of the recorded interview.
Interviewers questioned individuals on their life history, employment, and areas of expertise. The topics covered in the interviews range widely. Topics include various businesses and institutions including Wampler Foods, Pilgrim's Pride, Western State Hospital, the Virginia State Hospital, Shenandoah National Park. Several interviews cover the poultry industry, including interviews with poultry growers, processing workers, processing managers, and people who manage by-products. Other interviews address topics such as homelessness, the prison system, veterans issues, LGBTQ issues, Native Americans, immigrant experiences, agriculture, and labor and civil rights activism.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series, based on the time of accession. Series 1: Oral History Interviews, 2005-2007, is comprised of interviews conducted by students in Dr. Kerr's course: HIST 339: Selected Themes in U.S. History.
Series 2: Oral History Interviews, 2006-2009, is comprised of 20 interviews conducted by students in Dr. Kerr's courses, HIST 339: US Environmental History and HIST 441/641: Oral History and Social Justice.
Folders are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the interviewee.
Index Terms
Genre and Form Terms:
oral histories (literary works)
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, 2005–2007
  - 29-1: Daniels, Greyson, interviewed by Shannon Gavin, March 15, 2006
    Scope and Contents
    Explores the experiences of this native of Newport News, Virginia, who served four years in Virginia's correctional system before being transferred to the Gemeinschaft Home in Harrisonburg pending his release. The Gemeinschaft Home is a Transitional Therapeutic Community (TTC) that provides counseling, job training and responsibility skills to ex-convicts about to re-enter the community. Describes the events that led to Daniels' sentencing, his incarceration and his experiences in the Gemeinschaft Home program. Discusses Daniels' impressions of the strengths and weaknesses of the TTC program and his steady rise resident to councilor within the system.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 15, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Original audio-disc, March 15, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-001)
    - Preservation master, March 15, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
      Other Finding Aids
      audio-disc
  - 29-2: Farrish, John D., interviewed by Scott Burwell, December 5, 2005
    Describes the history of the Teamsters Union in the Shenandoah Valley, specifically Teamsters Local 29, which was formed in 1963. Farrish joined the union as a driver in 1975, eventually rising to the post of president of the union in 1997. Discusses general working conditions in the Shenandoah Valley and issues of race and migration. Also mentioned are union member benefits, the matter of 'right to work' and 'closed shop' states, and the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 5, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Original audio-disc, December 5, 2005 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-002)
    - Preservation master, December 5, 2005 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-3: Fisher, Betty Kilby, interviewed by Carrie MacLeod, March 28, 2007
    Describes her experiences as an African American student in Virginia during the early years of school desegregation in the 1950s and 1960s. Describes the policy of "massive resistance" whereby the governor of Virginia closed the public schools in an effort to avoid integration. Recalls the efforts of her father, James W. Kilby, who named Fisher as a plaintiff in the Virginia court case Betty Ann Kilby v. Warren County Board of Educationwhich ultimately lead to the integration of Warren County High School in 1958. Concludes with a discussion of her life after graduation and her reflections on the lessons learned over the past fifty years of school desegregation.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 28, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Original audio-disc, March 28, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-003)
    - Preservation master, March 28, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-4: Johnson, Mabel, interviewed by Hayden Van Dyke, March 21, 2006
    Describes her experience working in several poultry processing plants in the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia for more than twenty years, primarily as a union steward for the United Food and Commercial Workers union (UFCW) from 1977 until her retirement in 1986. Discusses her early childhood and family life and her election to shop steward, succeeding her husband, who held the post at the time of his death in 1977. Discusses the working conditions, wages and occupational hazards in the industry during those years and her commitment to ensuring worker's rights through organized labor unions. Recalls walk out strikes at several poultry plants in the Valley during the 1970s.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 21, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Original audio-disc, March 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-004)
    - Preservation master, March 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-5: Layman, Allen, interviewed by Hayden Van Dyke, April 5, 2006
    Records Layman's experiences as a thirty year employee of the Western State Hospital in Staunton, Virginia. Layman was the president of the local chapter of the United Radio, Electrical and Machine Workers of America (UE), the labor union representing para-professional and housekeeping staff at the psychiatric facility. Recalls various occasions when the UE was asked to arbitrate on behalf of hospital staff members. Discusses the perceived attitudes of some hospital managers toward the classified staff, cases of alleged malfeasance by hospital management, and the overall effects on employee retention.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 5, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Original audio-disc, April 5, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-005)
    - Preservation master, April 5, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-6: Maul, Kris, interviewed by Joanna Lee, March 28, 2006
    Examines the impact of incarceration on a prisoner's family members. This interview, which was given with his permission and the permission of his mother, records the thoughts and feelings of the eight year old son of an inmate serving a sentence in the Virginia correctional system.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 28, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Original audio-disc, March 28, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-006)
    - Preservation master, March 28, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-7: Michael, Greg, interviewed by Joanna Lee, April 23, 2006
    Discusses the experiences of a West Virginia farmer who served fourteen years in prison for selling marijuana in the 1990s. Topics include his early family life, his arrest and the events surrounding his trial and sentencing. He discusses the conditions in the federal prisons in West Virginia and Maryland in which he served his time. Relates the coping strategies he employed while incarcerated, such as teaching yoga to fellow inmates, working in the prison kitchens and writing poetry, some of which was published.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 23, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Original audio-disc, April 23, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-007)
    - Preservation master, April 23, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-8: Morrison, Pat, interviewed by Amy R. Larrabee, April 21, 2006
    Records the reminiscences a life-long Virginia native who moved to the Harrisonburg area as a child in the 1950s. Describes her early family life, school days, and other experiences growing up in the Shenandoah Valley. Discusses race relations and school integration during the 1960s, her marriage after graduation from high school, and life as a military wife stationed in Germany. Describes her work as a food service technician at Harrisonburg High School and Waterman Elementary School, and changes to the school lunch program over the years.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 21, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Original audio-disc, April 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-008)
    - Preservation master, April 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-102)
  - 29-9: Patterson, Julia (with Mercedes Williams), interviewed by Amy R. Larrabee, March 11, 2006
    Records the reminiscences of an African American woman who worked as a live-in domestic worker in New York, New Jersey and Virginia for more than sixty years. Discusses her early family life as one of seventeen siblings growing up in rural Virginia in the early decades of the 20th century. Ms. Patterson is occasionally joined by her half-sister Mercedes "Sadie" Williams at various points throughout the interview. Recalls daily life under Segregation as well as wartime rationing in the 1940s. Closes with a discussion of her life since her retirement at the age of 86.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 11, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Original audio-disc, March 11, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-009)
  - 29-10: Peachy, Tom, interviewed by Carrie MacLeod, April 12, 2006
    Records the reminiscences of Tom Peachy, a long time resident of Warren County, Virginia. Describes his early family life and education. Recalls the decision by Warren County to close the public schools in an effort to avoid school desegregation in 1958. Discusses his views on integration and equal rights, as well as his secondary education and work history. Peachy worked as a missionary, a teacher and a psychologist over the course of his professional life. Closes with Peachy's reflections on how his training as a psychologist has shaped his religious beliefs and world view.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 12, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Original audio-disc, April 12, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-010)
    - Preservation master, April 12, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-102)
  - 29-11: Robinson, Monica, interviewed by Nicole Snyder, March 23, 2006
    Records the experiences of Monica Robinson, a Special Education teacher and community activist who has lived in Harrisonburg, Virginia, since the mid-1970s. Describes her family life, early education and changing social and economic conditions in Harrisonburg. Discusses the legacy of urban renewal on Harrisonburg's minority neighborhoods in the 1950s and 1960s as described by Robinson's mother and other long-time residents. Discusses Robinson's involvement with the local chapter of Copwatch, an all-volunteer citizen group that observes and records interactions between police officers and Harrisonburg's growing minority populations. Describes the impact of the federal government's "Weed and Seed" which was designed to remove criminal elements from low income neighborhoods while encouraging civic improvements at the local level.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 23, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Original audio-disc, March 23, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-011)
    - Preservation master, March 23, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-102)
  - 29-12: Shelton, Garfield, interviewed by Nicole Snyder, March 3, 2006
    Records the experiences of Garfield Shelton, who provides a general life history from the perspective of a person living with schizophrenia in Harrisonburg, Virginia.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 3, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Original audio-disc, March 3, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-012)
    - Preservation master, March 3, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-13: Swarts, Crysta, interviewed by Heather Campbell, March 2, 2006
    Records an interview with Crysta Swarts, a student at James Madison University, who relates her life experiences as a person who identifies as bisexual. Describes her family and social life and the impact of her sexual identity on those relationships. Discusses her dating experiences with men and women over the previous five years, and the discrimination she sometimes experiences. Reflects on her religious beliefs, the positive aspects of her life, and her plans for the future.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 2, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Original audio-disc, March 2, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-013)
    - Original audio-disc, March 2, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-014)
    - Preservation master, March 2, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-14: Velazquez, Alice, interviewed by Amanda Harris, March 30, 2006
    Records the life of Alice Velazquez from her childhood to her current endeavors in Harrisonburg, Virginia. She discusses her family situation as a child, jobs she has had throughout her life, her marriage, her children, and her housing opportunities in Harrisonburg after moving from New York state.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 30, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Original audio-disc, March 30, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-015)
    - Preservation master, March 30, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-101)
  - 29-15: Wills, Travis, interviewed by Ellen K. Donnelly, April 21, 2006
    Records the life experiences of Travis Wills, a 21-year old Virginia native residing in Harrisonburg. Describes his experience as the only openly gay student in a rural Virginia high school and of the difficulties faced by the gay and lesbian community in the Shenandoah Valley. Discusses his religious convictions and his thoughts on the roots of homophobia in society. Reflects on the changes that have been slowly occurring in the schools since his graduation and on Harrisonburg's growing gay community.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 21, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Original audio-disc, April 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-016)
    - Preservation master, April 21, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-102)
  - 29-16: JMU Professor, interviewed by Ellen Donnelly, May 1, 2006
    This interview with a long-time faculty member at James Madison University recounts his experiences as a gay man living and working in Harrisonburg for more than 25 years. Discusses his own college years, when he first realized he was gay and describes the social conditions at the time for gays and lesbians. Reflects on his teaching experiences at JMU, his religious views, and Harrisonburg's growing gay community.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, May 1, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Original audio-disc, May 1, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-017)
    - Preservation master, May 1, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-102)
  - 29-17: "Joe," interviewed by Ellen Donnelly, March 16, 2006
    Records the life experiences of "Joe", a student at James Madison University, who came out to his family and friends as being gay when he was in high school. Discusses the day to day realities of growing up gay in the very conservative city of Lynchburg, Va., comparing it with the greater freedoms he has experienced in Harrisonburg. Discusses his views on dating, politics, equal rights for gays and lesbians, and the issues still facing that community.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 16, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Original audio-disc, March 16, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-018)
    - Preservation master, May 1, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-102)
  - 29-18: Mr. Armstrong, interviewed by Lorraine White, April 14, 2006
    Records the experiences of Mr. Armstrong, an ex-convict residing in Virginia. Describes the events leading to his arrests and convictions as a young man and his experiences while serving his sentences in various jails and penitentiaries in Virginia. Discusses the conditions he encountered while incarcerated, his family relationships, interaction with law enforcement, and his efforts to start a new life in the years since his release. Includes comments by one of Armstrong's siblings regarding the effects of being related to a convict has on the inmate's family members, especially in a small, rural community.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 14, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Original audio-disc, April 14, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-019)
    - Preservation master, April 14, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-103)
  - 29-19: Miss Hughes, interviewed by Heather Campbell, April 14, 2006
    Records an interview with Hughes, a student at James Madison University, who relates her life experiences as a bisexual, African American woman. Describes her family and social life and the impact of her sexual identity on those relationships. Discusses her dating experiences with men and women over the previous six years and the discrimination she sometimes experiences regarding her bisexuality. Reflects on her religious beliefs, the positive aspects of her life and her plans for the future.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 14, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Original audio-disc, April 14, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-020)
    - Preservation master, April 14, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-103)
  - 29-20: Mr Scott, interviewed by Lorraine White, April 9, 2006
    Records the experiences of Mr. Scott, an ex-convict residing in Virginia. Describes the events leading to his arrests and trial and his experiences while serving his sentences in various jails and penitentiaries in Virginia. Discusses the conditions he encountered while incarcerated, his family relationships and his efforts to start a new life in the years since his release.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 9, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Original audio-disc, April 9, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-100)
    - Preservation master, April 9, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-103)
- Series 2: Oral History Interviews, 2006–2009
  - 29-21: Al Saadun, Nasser, interviewed by Dan Brennan, April 9, 2009
    Nasser Abdulsalam Al Saadun of Harrisonburg, Virginia speaks about his experience coming to the Shenandoah Valley as a refugee from Iraq. Al Saadun discusses his work as an interpreter for the British and US armies and the events causing him to seek refugee status in the United States. He talks about growing up in Basra, the challenges he and his family experience as refugees in Harrisonburg, the experiences of refugees more generally, and his work with the Islamic Center of Shenandoah.
    - Original audio-disc, April 9, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-021)
    - Preservation master, April 9, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-096)
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 9, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 29-22: Allen, Robert, interviewed by Patrick Callahan, December 1, 2008
    Robert Allen, a civil engineer, discusses the environmental reclamation aspect of coal mining in Southwest Virginia, including Lee County, Dickenson, Wise and Buchanan Counties. He describes the coal industry with emphasis on union activities, environmental regulations, labor mechanization, community responses to coal mining, and the future of fossil fuels.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 1, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Original audio-disc, December 1, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-022)
  - 29-23: Alvarado, Juan, interviewed by Terrence Haliburton, April 9, 2007
    Juan Alvarado discusses his work as a forklift driver at a poultry plant in Harrisonburg, Virginia, He describes his early life, growing up on a farm Queretaro, Mexico, his day-to-day work at the poultry plant, and his plans for the future.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 9, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Original audio-disc, April 9, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-023)
    - Preservation master, April 9, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-24: Anderson, Daniel, interviewed by Senay Gebremedhin, April 23, 2009
    NO TRANSCRIPT
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 23, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Original audio-disc, April 23, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-024)
    - Preservation master, April 23, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-25: Anonymous Female, interviewed by Tiffany Cole, March 6, 2009
    Records an interview with an anonymous narrator who resides in Harrisonburg, Virginia. She discusses her life, including her experiences with homelessness. She describes her childhood in Detroit and Tennessee, the state of social services in Harrisonburg, Virginia, stereotypes and misconsceptions of people who are experiencing homelessness, and time she spent in the Mercy House, a family focused homeless shelter in Harrisonburg, Virginia. She also discusses her current work, and her hopes for her children and step-children.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 6, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Original audio-disc, March 6, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-025)
    - Preservation master, March 6, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-099)
  - 29-26: Anonymous Male, interviewed by Tim Van Schaich, March 7, 2007
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 7, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Original audio-disc, March 7, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-026)
  - 29-27: Anonymous Male, interviewed by Chelsea Hersch, April 19, 2007
    Records an interview with an anonymous narrator in the Shenandoah Valley, who discusses his work as a poultry processing employee with over thirteen years of experience in the poultry business. The narrator immigrated to the United States from Mexico when he was seventeen years old, and eventually settled in Harrisonburg, Virginia. He discusses his work experience at Cargill poultry plant in Dayton, Virginia, and discusses topics such as machine safety, benefits and insurance, and what it is like to work on the assembly line.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 19, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Original audio-disc, April 19, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-027)